Guide to the Antonio Márquez Papers, 1877-2010 (bulk 1932-2010)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Antonio Márquez Papers
1877-2010
1932-2010
Márquez, Antonio, 1923-
21 cubic feet (60 boxes)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Collection includes correspondence, subject files, research notes and associated correspondence. Files hold typescripts, manuscripts and drafts. Journals and diaries include poetry and sketches. Press clippings document reviews of Márquez’s writings. Collection also includes some photographic documentation relating to Márquez’s personal and professional life. Personal papers contain some correspondence, academic administrative papers, as well as family genealogy documentation.
Biographical Note
Dr. Antonio Márquez (b. 1923 - d. 2010), poet, painter and academic, was born in Arriate, Malaga, Spain. As a young man he studied in Spain under the Jesuit order, and went on to study in Ecuador (1951- 1953) as a member of that order, then went on to to study in the U.S. at the Seminary of St. Andrew’s in Hyde Park, NY. Márquez completed his Doctorate in Philosophy of Religion from Pontifical University of Salamanca, Spain in 1970.
Dr. Márquez’s research and writings focused on heterodox mysticism, Spanish cultural history, literature and religion and the Spanish Inquisition. Márquez spent his first sabbatical year in Spain (1965-1966) collecting bibliographic texts on these subjects, followed by two additional years writing his dissertation on Origenes y naturaleza del Ilumismo en Castilla, which was published under the title, Los Alumbrados: Origenes y Filosofia, 1525-1559 [Madrid: Taurus, 1972, 2nd ed., 1980 ].
Márquez taught as a professor of Spanish at Bennett College and Vassar College, and was chairman of the Foreign Language Department at Dutchess Community College (1971 - 1975). From 1957-1958 he served as the Editor in Chief of the Madrid-based cultural publication, Indice.
Dr. Márquez’s artwork has been exhibited in Spain and the US. A collection of his visual work resides at the Francis Lehman Loeb Art Center, Vassar College.
Chronology
1923 Born in Arriate, Malaga, Spain
1951 Receives Masters degree in Philosophy
1951-1953 Studies Modern History in Ecuador
1954-1967 Studies painting with Herrera Zapata in New York, Havana and Paris
1957-1958 Editor in Chief of Madrid-based cultural publication, Indice
1958 Marries Margaret Logan (historian of Hyde Park), Hyde Park, NY
1960-1967 Chairman, Department of Modern Languages, Bennett College
1965-1966 Research sabbatical, Spain
1968-1970 Studied in Spain writing dissertation, Origenes y naturaleza del ilumismo en Castilla
1968-1978 Researched and contributed to transcription and publication of Milagros Ortega-Costa Proceso de la Inquisicion contra Maria de Cazalla
1970 Receives PhD, Philosophy, from Pontifical University of Salamanca, 1970
1971-1975 Department Head of Foreign Languages, Dutchess Community College
1976 Visiting professor, Vassar College
1995 Art exhibition "A Mystical Tale," Ronda, Malaga, Spain
2000 Art exhibition "Confessions," Vassar College
Scope and Content Note
The Papers of Dr. Antonio Márquez documents a longstanding interest in the historical documentation of Spanish cultural history, mysticism, literature and religion. Márquez’s research focused on Spanish heterodox mysticism, and the alumbrados. His interest in the value of properly transcribed trial records, beyond available Latin texts typically found in the translations of these records, led him to study documentation of the trial, Milagros Ortega-Costa Proceso de la Inquisicion contra Maria de Cazalla. A rejected 1985 NEH proposal (Series II, Subject Files) documents Dr. Márquez’s interest in the transcription, annotation and interpretation of such records.
The bulk of Dr. Márquez’s typescripts and subject files date from the late 1950s through the 1990s, many of which include associated correspondence and administrative files, some documenting his travel logistics as well as related research notes.
A substantial volume of correspondence is filed in the first series (Series I, 17 boxes, 1953-2009). One complete document box (1957 -1978) contains correspondence related to Márquez’s tenure as Editor-in-Chief at the Spanish publication, Indice. Folder titles from Series II (Subject Files, 1932-2007) and Series III (Typescripts, 1950-1995) are titled as filed by Dr. Márquez. Typescripts include drafts of Dr. Márquez’s autobiography, with editorial notes from his friend and colleague, Steve Clark (Senior Editor, Paris Review).
The collection also includes reviews of Dr. Márquez’s writings (Series IV, Pressclippings 1957-2007), drafts of poetry (Series V, 1964-1999). One complete document box contains photographic prints (Series X, 1950-2004) which document friends and colleagues in Spain, from as early as 1950 through 2000s to personal life in and around Hyde Park, NY (1980s-2000).
Journals and diaries, a number of which include documentation of Márquez’s travels, artwork, sketches and drafts of poetry are included in Series VIII (1958-2010). Series VII (Personal Papers, 1953-2003) include documentation from Dr. Márquez’s start as a young seminarian, and holds birth, military and academic certificates, as well as Márquez’s early academic transcripts.
Access
This collection is open for research according to the
regulations of the Vassar College Archives and Special Collections Library
without any additional restrictions.
Separated Materials
Márquez’s artwork is currently housed in the Department of Hispanic Studies, Vassar College.
Digital versions of these paintings can be found in Vassar College's Digital Library.
Subject Headings
Names:
Cazalla, Mary; Cervantes Saavedra, Miguel de, 1547-1616; Clark, Steve (poet); Alcaraz, Pedro Ruiz de; Cruz, Isabela de la, active 17th century; Llorente, Cornelia; León, Luis de, 1527-1591; Knopf, Alfred A., 1892-1984; Netanyahu, Binyamin; Tàpies, Antoni, 1923-2012; Tillich, Paul, 1886-1965; Valente, José Angel
Organizations:
Dutchess Community College; Bennett College (Millbrook, N.Y.); Índice (Madrid, Spain); Vassar College; SILVEMA: Boletín de la Asociación Malagueña para la Protección de la Vida Silvestre
Subjects:
Alumbrados; Catholic Church and world politics; Mysticism; Inquisition--Spain; Poetry
Places:
Bogotá (Colombia); Hyde Park (Dutchess County, N.Y.); Ronda (Málaga, Spain)
Document Types:
Diaries; Manuscripts; Photographs
VCL Categories:
Art and Artists; Literature and Writing; Religion; Vassar College
Encoding Information
Encoded by Laura Streett, March 2014.
Custodial History
Bequeathed to the Vassar College Department of Hispanic Studies in 2010.
Acquisition Information
Transferred from the Vassar College Department of Hispanic Studies in 2013.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into ten series. Correspondence is arranged chronologically by year, as found when accessioned to Vassar Archives. The collection is not indexed by name, unless otherwise noted in the container list. Folders contain letters both from and to Antonio Márquez.
Series List
- Series I. Correspondence, 1953-2009; (17 boxes)
  Letters from noteworthy correspondents found while processing the collection were filed by year and name of correspondent. See Boxes 2, 4, 5, 6, and 14.
- Series II. Subject Files, 1932-2007; (16 boxes)
- Series III. Typescripts, 1950-1995; (25 boxes)
- Series IV. Writings, Published Works, 1958-2000; (1 box)
- Series V. Writings, Poetry, 1964-1999; (2 boxes)
- Series VI. Press Clippings, 1957-2007; (1 folder)
- Series VII. Personal Papers, 1953-2003; (2 boxes and 4 folders)
- Series VIII. Diaries/Journals, 1958-2010; (7 boxes)
- Series IX. Printed Material, 1877, 1968-2000; (1 box)
- Series X. Photographs, 1950-2004; (1 box and 2 folders)
Container List
- Series I. Correspondence
  - Correspondence, 1953-1959 (Box 1)
    Includes correspondence regarding Sobre La Situacion de Espana.
  - Correspondence, 1959-1967 (Box 2)
    Includes correspondence (3) signed letters, from Knopf, Alfred A., regarding submitted manuscript (Catholic Politics), April - June, 1960.
  - Correspondence, 1968-1974 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1974-1976 (Box 4)
    Includes correspondence from Stamm, James - NYU.
  - Correspondence, 1977-1978 (Box 5)
    Includes correspondence regarding job applications and potential teaching positions; Includes correspondence from Cano, Jose Luis (1978-1998) and manuscript: La Ideologia de Cervantes.
  - Correspondence, 1978-1981 (Box 6)
    Includes correspondence regarding Literatura e Inquisicion; correspondence from Hamilton, Alastair (1979) re: Alumbrados; correspondence from Netanyahu, Benjamin (1979, 1981) regarding Litaratura e Inquiscion.
  - Correspondence, 1980-1981 (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, 1981-1982 (Box 8)
  - Correspondence, 1982-1984 (Box 9)
  - Correspondence, 1984-1986 (Box 10)
  - Correspondence, 1987-1988 (Box 11)
  - Correspondence, 1989-1990 (Box 12)
  - Correspondence, 1991-1997 (Box 13)
  - Correspondence, 1998-2003 (Box 14)
    Includes correspondence from Dominquez, Jose (2003).
  - Correspondence, 2004-2005 (Box 15)
  - Correspondence, 2006-2009 (Box 16)
  - Correspondence, 1957-1978 (Box 17)
    Correspondence held as filed by Márquez, regarding work at Indice Magazine.
- Series II. Subject Files
  - Alumbrados (manuscript photocopy, 1623, Dealgunas Relaciones ...) (Folder 32.1)
  - Apotaciones Para la Historia Externa de Los Indices Expurgatorios Espanoles, 1952; (photocopy) (Folder 18.1)
  - Art Exhibition, "Confessions,", 2000 (Folder 18.2)
  - Art Exhibitions, Ronda Spain, Vassar College, 2000-2007 (Folder 18.3)
  - Autobiography in the Hispanic World, Torres Villarroel, 1999 (Folders 18.4 - 18.6)
  - Bibliotheca Bibliographica Histoire Sanctae Inquisitionis, 1982-1987 (Folder 32.2)
  - Biografia Sucinta de S.M. Don Juan Carlos I Rey de Espana, 1976 (Folder 32.3)
  - Bishop, Elizabeth, finding aid draft, 1993 (Folder 18.7)
  - Braman, Edward, 1873 (Folder 18.8)
  - Caracas Venezuela, includes correspondence with Martinez, A. Fernandez, 1959 (Folder 18.9)
  - Catolicismo y Catolicismo Franquista (Folder 18.10)
  - Cervantes (Folders 18.11 - 18.13)
  - Cervantes, Avellandeda, 1986 (Folder 32.4)
  - Cervantes, biography, reference materials, 1989 (Folders 32.5 - 32.6)
  - Cervantes, censorship, undated (Folder 19.1)
  - Cervantes, ideology, undated (Folders 32.7 - 32.8)
  - Cervantes, including correspondence re Anthropolos periodical, 1989 (Folder 19.2)
  - Cervantes, Portait of Cervantes, 1998-2005 (Folder 19.3)
  - Cervantes, research notes, undated (Folder 19.4)
  - Cervantes, Santander, 1981 (Folder 32.9)
  - Clark, Marga, 1982-2008 (Folder 19.5)
  - Conference, Galileo y La Heterodoxia, 12th conference on medieval studies, 1977-1987 (Folder 32.10)
  - Corpus Reformatorum, Hispanorum Project, 1970-1977 (Folders 19.6 -19.10)
  - Corpus Reformatorum Italicorum, 1977-1978 (Folder 19.11)
  - Culpas Contra Luis de Beteta, undated; (transcription photocopy) (Folders 32.11 - 32.17)
  - Dario Fo, Tony Mitchell, undated; (photocopy) (Folder 19.12)
  - Enrique Marin Higuero, 1999-2000 (Folder 19.13)
  - Fray Luis de Leon, Dosprocesos Singulares, undated (Folder 19.14)
  - Fray Luis de Leon, mystical work, undated (Folders 20.1 - 20.5)
  - Fray Luis de Leon, Teologo (Salvador Munoz Iglesias), 1950; (photocopy) (Folder 32.18)
  - GED coursework lessons (Arco Books), 1988 (Folders 31.1 - 31.8)
  - German Bleiberg, poetry, 1940; (photocopy) (Folder 32.19)
  - Inquisition - Arbor Magazine, iconography, Llorente, includes Index Librorum Prohibitorum, 1969-1986; (photocopy) (Folders 20.6 - 21.7)
  - Inquisition, Arrabel, Indice Magazine, 1977-1983 (Folder 21.8)
  - Inquisition, Garcia Lorca, undated (Folders 21.9 - 21.10)
  - Inquistiion, Llorente, undated (Folder 21.11)
  - Instruciones del Santo Oficio de la Inquisicion, 1630, undated; (photocopy) (Folder 21.12)
  - Italian Institute for Philosophical Studies, 1987-1989 (Folder 22.1)
  - Joachim of Flora, Speculum, Vol. 7, 1932; (photocopy) (Folder 22.2)
  - Julia de Burgos, 2003 (Folder 22.3)
  - La Corona de Aragon, Royal Chancery, Variedades Edicto de Los Reyes Catolicos, 1492, undated; (photocopy) (Folder 32.21)
  - Liberation Theology, undated (Folder 22.4)
  - Literatura E Inquistion en Espana, 1478-1834, resource materials, undated (Folders 22.5 - 23.12)
  - Literature, for and against Spanish Inquisition, undated (Folder 32.22)
  - Literature, Spanish, 1999-2004 (Folder 24.1)
  - Manuscripts submitted to Márquez - from Thomas Elias & Nilsa Rodriguez Jaca, 1974-2002 (Folder 24.2)
  - Márquez autobiography, notes, undated (Folder 24.3)
  - Márquez autobiography, reference material, 1997-1999 (Folder 24.4)
  - Middlebury College, VT, coursework notes and essay titled New Symbols or New Religion, 1963 (Folders 31.9 - 31.10)
  - Miguel de Cervantes Saavedra, 1948 (Folder 24.5)
  - Mysticism (Acta Apostolicae Sedis, Francisco Marcos del Rio, Juan de Quintana, Michael Servet, Juan de Valdes, 1971-1987 (Folders 24.6 - 25.4)
  - Normas de Transcripcion y Edicion de Textos y Documentos, undated; (photocopy) (Folder 32.23)
  - Noticia Biografica de Llorente, Cornelia, 1984 (Folder 25.5)
  - Philosophy of Religion, 1974-2007 (Folder 25.6)
  - Potential Texts for Catalogs, Magazines (Iconolgy, Lapidario O Breve Son Desi), 1995 (Folder 25.7)
  - Proceso de Alcaraz, folios 327-461, undated; (photocopy of original manuscript, including notes and summaries) (Folders 32.24 - 33.4)
  - Proceso de Maria de Cazalla, notes and research, 1971 (Folder 33.5)
  - Reference Material, sketches and visual resource material, 1960-1970 (Folder 33)
  - Regional Conference, PCE, Ronda, 1979 (Folder 33.7)
  - Research notes, Los Alumbrados, undated (Folders 25.8 - 26.6)
  - Research notes, misc., 2001-2004 (Folders 27.1 - 27.3)
  - Research notes, index card file, undated (Folder 34)
  - Ronda, Jornadas de Estudio, 1979 (Folders 33.8 - 33.11)
  - Ronda, town hall files, 1987 (Folder 33.12)
  - Ronda/Malaga, Cuevas de San Anton, 1980-1990 (Folder 27.4)
  - Ronda/Malaga, Spain, 1980-1999 (Folders 27.5 - 29.1)
  - Sadilles y Alumbrados, Parte Quinta, 1941-1951; (photocopy) (Folders 29.2 - 29.3)
  - Science and the Inquistion, reference materials, Arbor Journal, 1986 (Folders 29.4 - 29.7)
  - Silvema Association, includes correspondence and newsletters, 1984-1991 (Folder 33.13)
  - Society in Change, Inquisition, Brooklyn College, 1983 (Folder 29.8)
  - Spanish Inquisition and Free Masonry, undated (Folder 33.15)
  - Spanish Inquisition, Cornell University coursework, 1976 (Folder 31.11)
  - Spanish Literature, Vassar coursework, 1976 (Folder 31.12)
  - Spanish Reformation, coursework, 1976 (Folder 31.13)
  - Spanish Reformers of the XVI & XVII Centuries, Guggenheim Foundation, 1977 (Folder 29.9)
  - Spanish, written expression, high school examination teaching materials, 1983 (Folders 31.14 - 31.18)
  - Symposium, Inquisition & Censorship, Internat'l University, Santander, 1982 (Folder 30.1)
  - Symposium, International Association de Hispanistas, Toronto, Canada, 1977 (Folder 30.2)
  - Symposium, International Symposium - The Spanish Inquisition and the Inquisitorial Mind, 1983 (Folder 30.3)
  - Symposium, Spanish Inquisition and the Renaissance Theater, NYU, 1975 (Folder 30.4)
  - Tapies, Antoni, 1947-1972, art catalog, undated; (photocopy) (Folder 30.5)
  - Torres, Antonio Molina, 1966 (Folder 30.6)
  - Transcription of Trial Records, Pedro Ruiz de Alcaraz - rejected NEH Proposal, 1985 (Folders 30.7 - 30.9)
  - Universidad de Salamanca, Seminario de Historia de la Filosofia Espanola, 1982 (Folder 30.10)
  - Valente, Jose Angel, Three Lessons of Tenebrae, 1984 (Folder 30.11)
  - Villa de Arriate, town council minutes, 1979-1980 (Folder 33.16)
  - Zayas, Ana, undated (Folder 33.12)
- Series III. Typescripts
  - Catholic Politics, 1960; (two copies) (Folder 35.1)
  - Catholic Politics, 1960; (two copies) (Folder 35.2)
  - Catholic Politics, 1960 (Folder 36.1)
  - Catholic Politics, 1960 (Folders 36.2 - 36.4)
  - Catholic Politics, an exposition and the documents, with a reference to the presidential elections, 1960 (Folder 36.5)
  - Cervantes y la Inquisition, undated (Folder 36.6)
  - Concordato Entre la Santa Sede y Espana, 1960 (Folders 36.7 - 36.8)
  - De Espana y de los Espanoles un Testimonio, 1958 (Folder 37.1)
  - En El Pais de Jauja, undated; (playscript) (Folder 37.2)
  - Entre la Magia del Amor y la Magia de la Memoria, undated (Folder 37.3)
  - Errors About Civil Society, considered both in itself and in relation to the Church (includes manual re: how to write a term paper, 1947), undated (Folder 37.4)
  - Estado Actual de Los Estudios Inquisitoriales, undated (Folder 37.5)
  - Estado de Las Investigaciones Inquisitoriales, 1981 (Folder 37.6)
  - Fabula Mistica al Borde del Milenio, undated (Folder 37.7)
  - Fabula Mistica al Borde del Milenio, 1995 (Folder 37.8)
  - Fabula Mistica al Borde del Milenio, lecture notes, 1991 (Folder 37.9)
  - Fr. Alonso de la Fuente, 1950-1951; (transcription) (Folder 60.9)
  - Francisca Hernandez and Francisco Ortiz, 1865; (transcription) (Folders 38.1 - 38.7)
  - Humanisme et Religion Chez sor Juana Ines de La Cruz - book review, 1982 (Folder 38.8)
  - In the Manner of an Example, 1959 (Folder 38.9)
  - Inquisicion Espanola, 1970 (Folder 60.10)
  - La Ideologia de Cervantes, undated (Folder 38.10)
  - La Inquisicion En El Teatro y La Novela, undated (Folder 38.11)
  - Lecture, De Mistica Luisiana: Ser No Ser (Congreso Internacional, Salmanca), 1991 (Folder 60.16)
  - Lecture, Los Alumbrados, undated (Folder 38.12)
  - Lecture, Los Alumbrados, University de Salamanca, 1987 (Folder 60.17)
  - Lecture, Los Alumbrados, University de Zaragoza, 1983 (Folders 38.13 - 38.14)
  - Libros Prohibidos, 16th C, Edicion Critica de Los Indices, undated (Folder 39.1)
  - Literatura e Inquisicion en Espana - Grijalbo Publications, 1979 (Folder 39.2)
  - Literatura e Inquisicion en Espana 1478-1834, Vol I: Autores Procesados y Colaboradores; Vol II: Calidad y Efectos de la Censura, undated (Folder 60.11)
  - Literatura e Inquisicion en Saint Teresa - including notes, undated (Folder 60.12)
  - Los Alumbrados, Bibliographia, undated (Folder 60.13)
  - Los Alumbrados, Origenes y Filosofia, 1525-1559, 1968-1969 (Folders 39.3 - 39.6)
  - Los Alumbrados, Origenes y Filosofia, 1525-1559, final report with prologue by Pedro Sainz Rodriguez, 1968-1969 (Folders 39.7 - 39.10)
  - Los Indices, Universidad de Paris, undated (Folder 39.11)
  - Márquez Autobiography, undated (Folders 40.1 - 40.5)
  - Márquez Autobiography - including notes), 1993 (Folders 40.6 - 4013)
  - Origen y Caracterizacion, del Iluminismo, 1966 (Folder 41.1)
  - Paul Tillich, Spanish Mysticism - and supporting notes, undated (Folders 60.14 - 60.15)
  - Persona Humana y Psychologia Actual, 1951 (Folder 41.2)
  - Present State of Reformation in Spain - research resources & organizations, undated (Folder 41.3)
  - Proceso Inquisitorial Contra Pedro Ruiz de Alcaraz, undated (Folders 41.4 - 41.6)
  - Proceso Inquisitorial Contra Pedro Ruiz de Alcaraz - Corpus Reformation Hispanorum, undated (Folders 42.1 - 42.5)
  - Proceso Inquisitorial, Pedro Ruiz de Alcaraz vs. Isabel de la Cruz y Gaspar de Bedoya, Volumes I & II, undated; (transcription) (Folders 42.6 - 42.7)
  - Study: National Assembly of Laymen Organizations, Roman Catholic Church, 1960 (Folder 42.8)
  - The Spanish Theater of the Golden Age, a trilogy, undated (Folder 42.9)
  - Tribuna Libre, Inquisition, undated (Folder 42.10)
  - Work submitted to Márquez; Proceso de Maria de Cazalla, by Milagros Ortega Costa, undated (Folders 45.1 - 45.14)
  - Work submitted to Márquez; Sobre la Obra Latina de Fray Luis de Leon, by Joaquin Maristany, 1988 (Folder 60.23)
- Series IV. Writings, Published Works
  - Ciencia e Inquisicion: Proceso Inquisitorial/Proceso Historico -- LLULL, vol. 10, 1987 (Folder 46.1)
  - Dos Procesos Singulares: Los De Fray Luis De Leon y Antonio Enriquez Gomez -- Nueva Revista De Filogia Hispanica, No. 2, 1981 (Folder 46.2)
  - Estado Actual De Los Estudios Sobre La Inquisicion -- Arbor, No. 396, 1978 (Folder 46.3)
  - Juan de Valdes, Teologo De Los Alumbrados -- La Ciudad De Dios, Vol. 184, 1971 (Folder 46.4)
  - La Censura Inquisitorial Del Teatro Renacentista, 1514-1551 -- LLULL, 1980 (Folder 46.5)
  - Literatura e Inquisicion en Espana, 1980 (Folders 43.1 – 43.8)
  - Literatura e Inquisicion Sig Los XV y XVI, 2000 (Folders 60.8 – 60.19)
  - Los Alumbrados -- Madrid: Taurus Ediciones, 1972 (Folder 46.7)
  - Los Alumbrados, 2nd edition, introduction, 1980 (Folder 43.9)
  - Los Alumbrados, Origenes Y Filosofia (1525-1559) -- Madrid: Taurus Ediciones, 1980 (Folder 46.8)
  - Modus Vivendi -- Dialogo de Las Espanas, 1959 (Folder 46.6)
  - Por Un Guillen Total -- Insula, No. 435-436, 1983 (Folder 60.8)
  - Procesos de Alcaraz (including notes, edits), undated (Folders 43.10 - 44.6)
  - Science and the Inquisition, Arbor Journal, 1986 (Folders 60.20 - 60.22)
  - Sobre la Situacion, unpublished introduction, 2nd edition, 1959 (Folder 44.8)
  - Sobre la Situacion de Espana, 1958 (Folder 44.7)
  - La Ciudad De Dios, Vol. 184, 1968 (Folder 46.7)
  - Universidad E Inquisicion (I) -- Madrid: Arbor, Science, Thought & Culture, No. 522, 1989 (Folder 46.8)
- Series V. Writings, Poetry
  - Lapidario o Breve Son De Si, 1984-1995 (Folder 47.1)
  - Loose type and manuscripts, circa 1994 (Folder 47.2)
  - Poetry of Steve Clark (includes correspondence), 1995-1997 (Folders 47.3 – 47.4)
  - Poetry of Steve Clark, sketches and notations by Antonio Márquez, undated (Folder 48.1)
  - Poetry, Desde La Obscuridad - variaciones poeticas sobre el Libro de Job, 1957 (Folder 48.2)
  - Poetry, loose typescripts, 1964-1965 (Folder 48.3)
  - Sombra y Senora Mia, and other loose type and manuscripts, 1967-1999 (Folder 48.4)
  - Testamento, and other loose type and manuscripts, 1980s (Folder 48.5)
- Series VI. Press Clippings
  - Clippings, 1957-1970 (Folder 46.11)
  - Clippings, 1981-1989 (Folder 46.12)
  - Clippings, 1991-2007 (Folder 46.13)
  - Clippings, 1959-1982 (Folder 46.14)
    Includes reviews of Márquez writings.
  - Clippings, 1978 (Folder 60.7)
    Inquisition-related clippings.
- Series VII. Personal Papers
  - Academic transcripts, 1954-1971 (Folder 60.1)
  - Certificates, personal and academic, 1953-1987 (Folder 60.3)
  - Dutchess Community College, Tenure Arbitration Proceedings, 1966-1975 (Folder 60.2)
  - Dutchess Community College, Tenure Arbitration Proceedings, 1970-1974 (Folders 49.1 – 49.4)
  - Family genealogy, inheritance documentation (mother), will (father), 1976-1983 (Folder 60.4)
  - ID cards, undated (Folder 49.5)
  - Identification/certificates, birth, military, academic, 1953-1987 (Folder 49.6)
  - Passports, 1969-2003 (Folder 49.7)
  - Student evaluations, Vassar College Course and Faculty Evaluations, 1976-1977 (Folder 50.1)
  - Teaching Contracts, 1959-1987 (Folder 50.2)
  - Tenure petition, Dutchess Community College (includes grievance and termination documentation), 1973-1974 (Folders 50.3 – 50.7)
  - Yearbook, Bennett College, Millbrook, NY, 1967 (Folder 50.8)
- Series VIII. Diaries/Journals
  - 1958-1972 (Box 51)
  - 1973-1982 (Box 52)
  - 1983-1996 (Box 53)
  - 1988-1998 (Box 54)
  - 2001-2006 (Box 55)
  - 2006-2010 (Box 56)
  - 1964-2003 (Box 57)
  - La Paloma Colorada (includes sketches), undated (Folder 47.5)
- Series IX. Printed Material
  - Antonio Márquez, Confessions – Vassar College Art Exhibition Catalog, 2000 (Folder 58.1)
  - Entre El Mare Y El Hierro, Gines Serran, (poetry), 1984 (Folder 58.2)
  - Offprints/Reprints with inscriptions to Antonio Márquez, 1968-1992; (11 items) (Folder 58.3)